this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
ski radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society by IEEE software
Magazine online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host Jeff Doolittle I'm excited
to invite Ryan McGee as our guest on the
show today for a conversation about
using software to explore the nature of
reality
Ryan McGee is a postdoctoral scholar
research associate at ligo laboratory
Caltech he is interested in all things
gravitational waves but at the moment he
is mostly working to facilitate
multi-messenger astrophysics and probes
of the Dark Universe before arriving at
Caltech he defended his PhD at Penn
State
Ryan occasionally has free time outside
of physics On Any Given weekend he can
be found trying new food running and
hanging out with his deaf dog Poppy Ryan
welcome to the show
hey thanks Jeff for having me so we're
here to talk about how we use software
to explore the nature of reality and I
think just from your bio it lifts up
some questions in my mind can you
explain to us a little bit of context of
what problems you're trying to solve
with software so that as we get more
into the software side of things
listeners have context for what we mean
when you say things like multi-messenger
astrophysics or probes of the Dark
Universe yeah sure thing so I work
specifically on detecting gravitational
waves which were predicted around 100
Years Ago by Einstein but hadn't been
seen up until recently there was some
solid evidence that they might exist
back in the 70s I believe but it wasn't
until 2015 that we were able to observe
the impact of these signals directly so
gravitational waves are really exciting
right now in physics because they offer
a new way to observe our universe we're
so used to using various types of
electromagnetic waves or light to take
again what's going on and infer the
types of processes that are occurring
out in the cosmos but gravitational
waves let us probe things in a new
direction that are often complementary
to the information that we might get
from electromagnetic waves
so the first major thing that I work on
facilitating multi-messenger astronomy
really means that I'm interested in
detecting gravitational waves at the
same time as light or other types of
astrophysical signals The Hope here is
that when we detect things in both of
these channels we're able to get more
information than if we had just made the
observation in one of the channels alone
so I'm very interested in making sure
that we get more of those types of
discoveries interesting is it somewhat
analogous maybe to how humans have
multiple senses and if all we had was
our eyes we'd be limited in our ability
to experience the world but because we
also have tactile senses and auditory
senses that that gives us other ways in
order to understand what's happening
around us yeah exactly I think that's a
Perfect Analogy so gravitational waves
let's maybe get a little more of a sense
of of what that means what is their
Source what caused these and then how do
you measure them yeah so gravitational
waves are these really weakness
distortions in space-time the most
common way to think about them are
ripples in space-time that propagate
through our universe at the speed of
light so they're very very weak and
they're only caused by the most violent
Cosmic processes we have a couple of
different ideas on how they might form
out in the universe but right now the
only measured way is whenever we have
two very dense objects that wind up
orbiting one another and eventually
colliding into one another and so you
might hear me refer to these as binary
black holes or binary neutron stars
throughout this podcast now because
they're so weak we need to come up with
these very Advanced ways to detect these
waves we have to rely on very very
sensitive instruments and at the moment
the best way to do that is through
interferometry which basically relies on
using laser beams to help measure very
very small changes in length so we have
a number of these interface parameter
detectors around the earth at the moment
and the basic way that they work is by
sending a light beam down two
perpendicular arms where they hit a
mirror bounce back towards the source
and recombine to produce an interference
pattern and this interference pattern is
something that we can analyze for the
presence of gravitational waves if there
isn't a gravitational wave we don't
expect there to be any type of change in
the interference pattern because the two
arms have the exact same length but if a
gravitational wave passes through the
Earth and hits our detector it will have
this effect of slowly changing the
length of each of the two arms in a
rhythmic pattern that corresponds
directly to the properties of the source
as these two arms change very minutely
in length the interference pattern from
their recombined beam will begin to
change and we can map this change back
to the physical properties of the system
now the changes that we actually observe
are incredibly small and my favorite way
to think about this is by considering
the night sky so if you want to think
about how small these changes that we're
measuring are look up at the sky and
find the closest star that you can if
you were to measure the distance between
Earth and that star the changes that
we're measuring are equivalent to
measuring a change in in that distance
of one human hair's width from here to
what is it Proxima Centauri or yeah
exactly one human hair's width
difference over a three point something
light years yeah okay that's small it's
incredibly large distance and we're just
perturbing it by the smallest of amounts
and yet you know through the genius of a
number of Engineers we're able to make
that observation yeah if this wasn't a
software podcast we could definitely
geek out I'm sure on the hardened
Engineering in the physical world about
this process I imagine there's a lot of
challenges related to error and you know
a mouse could trip things up and things
of that nature which you know we might
get into as we talk about how you use
software to correct for those things but
clearly there's a lot of angles and
challenges that you have to face in
order to even come up with a way to
measure such a minute aspect of the
universe so let's shift gears a little
bit then into how do you use software at
a high level and then we'll kind of dig
down into the details as we go how is
software used used by you and by other
scientists to explore the nature of
reality yeah so I think the job of a lot
of people in science right now is kind
of at this interface between data
analysis and software engineering
because we write a lot of software to
solve our problems but at the heart of
it we're really interested in uncovering
some type of physical truth or being
able to play some type of statistical
constraint on whatever we're observing
so my work really starts after these
detectors have made all of their
measurements and software helps us to
facilitate the types of measurements
that we want to take and we're able to
do this both in low latency which I'm
quite interested in as well as in
archival analyzes so software is
extremely useful in terms of figuring
out how to analyze the data as we
collect it in as rapid of a way as
possible in terms of cleaning up the
data so that we get better measurements
of physical properties it really just
makes our lives a lot easier so there's
software I imagine on both the
collection side and then on the
real-time side and then on the analysis
side as well so you mentioned for
example the low latency immediate
feedback as opposed to post data
retrieval analysis what are the
differences there as far as how you
approach these things and where is more
of your work focused or is it in both
areas
so the software that I primarily work on
is stream based so what we're interested
in doing is as the data goes through the
collectors through the detectors there's
a post-processing pipeline which I won't
talk about now but the output of that
post-processing pipeline is data that we
wish to analyze and so my pipeline works
on analyzing that data as soon as it
comes in and continuously updating the
broader world with results so the Hope
here is that we can analyze this data
looking for gravitational wave
candidates and that we can alert partner
astronomers anytime there's a promising
candidate that rolls through the
pipeline I see so I imagine there's some
statistical constraints there where you
may or may not have discovered a
gravitational wave and then in the
archival world people can go in and try
to basically falsify whether or not that
truly was a gravitational wave but
you're looking for that initial signal
as the data is being collected yeah
that's right so we typically don't
broadcast our candidates to the world
unless we have a very strong indication
that the candidate is astrophysical of
course there are candidates that slip
through that wind up being noise or
glitches that we later have to go back
and correct our interpretation of and
you're right these archival analyzes
also help us to provide a final say on a
data set these are often done months
after we've collected the data and we
have a better idea of what the noise
properties look like what the the
mapping between the physics and the
interference pattern looks like so yeah
there's definitely a couple of steps to
this analysis are you also having to
collect data about the real world
environment around you know these
interference laser configurations for
example did an earthquake happen did a
hurricane happen did somebody sneeze I
mean is that it also being collected in
real time for later analysis as well
yeah and that's a really great question
and there's a couple of answers to that
the first is that the raw data we can
actually see evidence of these things so
we can look in the data and see when an
earthquake happened or when some other
violent event happened on Earth the more
rigorous answer is a little bit tougher
which is that you know at these
detectors I'm mainly talking about this
one data set that we're interested in
analyzing but in reality we actually
monitor hundreds of thousands of
different data sets at once and a lot of
these never really make it to me because
they're often used by these detector
characterization pipelines that help to
monitor the state of the detectors see
things that are going wrong Etc and so
those are really where I would say a lot
of these environmental impacts would
show up in addition to having some you
know more difficult to quantify impact
on the strain that we're actually
observing okay and then before we dig a
little bit deeper into the some of the
details of the software I imagine
there's also feedback loops coming back
from those Downstream pipelines that
you're using to be able to calibrate
your own statistical analysis of the
real-time data collection yeah that's
right so there's a couple of new
pipelines that try to incorporate as
much of that information as possible to
provide some type of data quality
statement and that's something that
we're working to incorporate on the
detection side as well okay so you
mentioned before and I feel like it's
pretty evident just from the last couple
minutes of our conversation that there's
certainly an intersection here between
the software engineering aspects of
using software to explore the niche of
reality and then the data science
aspects of doing this process as well so
maybe speak to us a little bit about
where you kind of land in that world and
then what kind of distinguishes those
two approaches with the people that you
tend to be working with so I would
probably say I am very close to the
center maybe just a touch more on the
data science side of things but yeah
it's definitely a spectrum inside of
science that's for sure so I think
something to remember about Academia is
that there's a lot of structure in it
that's not dissimilar from companies
that act in the software space already
so we have you know professors which one
run these research Labs that have
graduate students that write their
software and do their analysis but we
also have staff scientists that work on
maintaining critical pieces of software
or infrastructure or database handling
there's really a broad spectrum of work
being carried out at all times and so a
lot of people often have their hands in
one or two piles at once I think you
know for us software engineering is
really the group of people that make
sure that everything is running smoothly
that all of our data analysis pipelines
are connected properly that we're doing
things as quickly as possible and I
would say you know the data analysis
people are more interested in writing
the models that we're hoping to analyze
in the first place so going through the
math and the statistics and making sure
that the software pipeline that we've
set up is producing the exact number
that we you know want to look at in the
future so in the software engineering as
you said it's more of a spectrum not a
hard distinction but give other
listeners maybe a sense of the flavor of
the tools that you and others in your
field might be using and what's
distinctive about that as it pertains to
software engineering versus data science
in other words is there overlap in the
tooling is there a distinction in the
tooling and what kind of languages tools
platforms are often being used in this
world yeah I'd say python is probably
the dominant language at the moment at
least for most of the people that I know
there's of course a ton of C as well I
would say those two are the most common
by far we also tend to handle our
databases using SQL and of course you
know we have more front-end stuff as
well but I'd say that's a little bit
more limited since we're not always the
best about real-time visualization stuff
although we're starting to you know move
a little bit more in that direction
interesting that's funny to me that you
said SQL that's surprising to me maybe
it's not to others but but it's just
interesting how SQL is kind of the way
we we deal with data for some reason I
would have thought it was different in
your world yeah it's got a lot of
singing power yeah SQL databases on
variations in space time interesting
yeah that's really cool so python as you
mentioned is is pretty dominant and
that's both in the software engineering
and the data science world yeah I would
say so yeah and then I imagine C is
probably more what you're doing when
you're doing control systems for the
physical instruments and things of that
nature yeah definitely the stuff that
works really close to the detector is
normally written those lower level
languages as you might imagine now are
there Specialists perhaps that are
writing some of that Control software
where maybe they aren't as trained in
the world of science but they are more
pure software Engineers or most of these
people scientists who also happen to be
software engineering capable that's an
interesting question I would probably
classify a lot of these people as mostly
software Engineers that said a huge
majority of them have a science
background of some sort whether they
went for a terminal Masters in some type
of engineering or they have a PhD and
decided they just like writing pure
software and not worrying about the the
physical implementations of some of the
downstream stuff as much so there is a
spectrum but I would say there's a
number of people that really focus
entirely on maintaining the software
stack that the rest of the community
uses interesting so while they have
specialized in software engineering they
still very often have a science
background but maybe their day-to-day
operations are more related to the
specialization of software engineering
yeah exactly yeah that's actually really
cool to hear too because it means you
don't have to be a particle physicist
you know the top tier in order to still
contribute to using software for
exploring fundamental physics oh
definitely and there are a lot of people
also that don't have a science
background and have just found some type
of Staff scientist role where here's how
scientist doesn't necessarily mean you
know they're getting their hands dirty
with the actual physics of it but just
that they are associated with some
academic group and writing software for
that group yeah although in this case
we're not getting our hands dirty we're
getting our hands warped first
which it did occur to me before when you
said we're talking about the width of
human hair from the distance from here
to Proxima Centauri which I think kind
of shatters our hopes for a warp drive
because gosh the energy to
enough space around a physical object in
order to move it through the universe
seems pretty daunting but again it was a
little far afield but it's disappointing
I'm sure for many of our listeners
so having no experience in exploring
fundamental physics or or science using
software I am curious from my
perspective mostly being in the business
software world for my career there are a
lot of times where we talk about good
software engineering practices and this
often shows up in different patterns or
practices that we basically were trying
to make sure our software is
maintainable we want to make sure it's
reusable hopefully we're trying to make
sure it's cost effective and it's high
quality so there's various patterns you
you know maybe you've heard of and maybe
you haven't you know single
responsibility principle open close
principle you know various patterns that
we use to try to determine if our
software is going to be maintainable and
of high quality and things of that
nature so I'm curious if there's
principles like that that might apply in
your field or maybe you have different
even ways of looking at it or talking
about it yeah I think they do I think
part of what can get confusing in
Academia is that we either use different
vocab to describe some of that or we
just have a slightly more loosey-goosey
approach to things we certainly strive
to make software as maintainable as
possible we don't want to have just a
singular point of contact for a piece of
code because we know that's just going
to be a failure mode at some point down
the line I imagine like everyone in
business software we work very hard to
keep everything in Version Control to
write unit tests to make sure that the
software is functioning properly and
that any changes aren't breaking the
software and of course we're always
interested in making sure that it is
very modular and as portable as possible
which is increasingly important in
Academia because although we've relied
on having dedicated Computing resources
in the past we're rapidly moving to the
world of cloud computing as you might
imagine where we'd like to use our
software on distributed resources which
has posed a bit of a challenge at times
just because a lot of the software
that's been previously developed has
been designed to just work on very
specific systems and so the the
portability of software has also been a
huge thing that we've worked towards
over the last couple of years oh
interesting so there are definitely
parallels between the two worlds and I
had no idea now that you say it it sort
of makes sense but you know moving to
the cloud it's like oh we're all moving
to the cloud there's a lot of challenges
with moving from monolithic to
distributed systems that I imagine
you're also having to deal with in your
world yeah yeah so are there any special
or specific constraints on the software
that you develop and maintain yeah I
think we really need to focus on it
being high availability and high
throughput at the moment so we want to
make sure that when we're analyzing this
data at the moment of collection that we
don't have any type of dropouts on our
side so we want to make sure that we're
always able to produce results if the
data exists so it's really important
that we have a couple of different
contingency plans in place so that if
something goes wrong at one site that
doesn't jeopardize the entire analysis
to facilitate having this entire
analysis running in in low latency we
also make sure that we have a very
highly parallelized analysis so that we
can have a number of things running at
once with essentially the lowest latency
possible
and I imagine there's challenges to
doing that so can you dig a little bit
deeper into what are your mitigation
strategies in your contingency
strategies for being able to handle
potential failures so that you can
maintain your basically your service
level agreements for availability
throughput and parallelization yeah so I
had mentioned before that you know we're
in this stage of moving from dedicated
compute resources to the cloud but this
is primarily true for some of the later
analyzes that we do a lot of the
archival analyzes for the time being
whenever we're doing something real time
we still have data from our detectors
broadcast to Central Computing sites
some are owned by Caltech some are owned
by the various detectors and then I
believe it's also University of
wisconsin-milwaukee and Penn State that
have compute sites that should be
receiving this data stream in ultra low
latency so at the moment our plan for
getting around any type of data dropouts
is to Simply run similar analyzes at
multiple sites at once so we'll run one
analysis at Caltech another analysis at
Milwaukee and then if there's any type
of power outage or availability issue at
one of those sites well then hopefully
there's just the issue at one and we'll
have the other analysis still running
still able to produce the results that
we need it sounds a lot like Netflix
being able to shut down one AWS region
and Netflix still works yeah yeah I
guess yeah it's very similar I mean pat
yourself on the back that's pretty cool
right
you know I don't know if you have chaos
monkeys running around actually you know
shutting things down of course for those
who know they don't actually just shut
down an AWS region willy-nilly like
there's a lot of planning a prep that
goes into it but that's great so you
mentioned for example broadcast maybe
explain a little bit for people aren't
familiar with what that means what is
that pattern what is that practice that
you're using when you broadcast in order
to have redundancy in your system so we
collect the data at the detectors
calibrate the data to have this physical
mapping and then we package it up into
this proprietary data format called
frames and we ship these frames off to a
number of sites as soon as we have them
basically so we will collect a couple of
seconds of data inside a single frame
send it to Caltech send it to Milwaukee
at the same time and then once that data
arrives there the pipelines are
analyzing it and it's this continuous
process where data from the detectors is
just immediately sent out to each of
these Computing sites so we've got this
idea now broadcast which is essentially
a messaging pattern we're sending
information out and you know in a true
broadcast fashion anyone could plug in
and receive the broadcast of course in
the case you described we have a couple
known recipients of the data that we
expect to receive the data are there
other patterns or practices that you use
to ensure that the data is reliably
delivered yeah so when we get the data
we know what to expect we expect to have
data flowing in at some Cadence in time
so to prevent or to help mitigate
against times where that's not the case
our pipeline actually has this feature
where if the data doesn't arrive it kind
of just circles in this holding pattern
waiting for the data to arrive and if
after a certain amount of time that
never actually happens it just continues
on with what it was doing but it knows
to expect the data from the broadcast
and it knows to wait some reasonable
length of time yeah and that's
interesting because in some applications
for example business applications you're
waiting and there's nothing until an
event occurs but in this case there's
always data there may or not be an event
a gravitational wave detection event but
there is always data in other words it's
the state of the interference pattern
which may or may not show presence of a
gravitational wave but there's always
you're always expecting data is that
correct yeah that's right there are
times where the interferometer is not
operating in which case we wouldn't
expect data but there's other
control signals in our data that help us
to you know be aware of the state of the
detector got it got it okay so control
signals along with the standard data
streams and again this is you know these
sound like a lot of standard messaging
patterns I'd be curious if we had time
to dig into how exactly those are
implemented and how similar those are to
other you know technologies that people
on the business side of the house might
be familiar with but in the interest of
time we probably won't be able to dig
too deep into some of those things well
let's switch gears here a little bit and
maybe speak a little bit to the volumes
of data that you're dealing with the
kinds of processing power that you need
you know I mean are is this old school
Hardware is enough we need terabytes and
zettabytes or like you know if you can
give us kind of a sense of the flavor of
the compute power the storage the
network transport what are we looking at
here as far as the constraints and the
requirements of what you need to get
your work done yeah so I think the data
flowing in from each of the detectors is
somewhere of the order of a gigabyte per
second
the data that we're actually analyzing
is originally shipped to us at about 16
kilohertz but it's also packaged with a
bunch of other data that can blow up the
file sizes quite a bit we typically use
about one sometimes two CPUs per
analysis job and here by analysis job I
really mean that we have some search
going on for a binary black hole or a
binary neutron star the signal space of
these types of systems is really large
so we parallelize our entire analysis
but for each of these little segments of
our analysis we typically rely on about
one to two CPUs and this is enough to
analyze all of the data that's coming in
in real time okay so not necessarily
heavy on CPU it might be heavy on the
CPUs you're using but not high quantity
but it sounds like the data itself is I
mean a gig per second for how long are
you capturing that gigabyte of data per
second for about a year
oh gosh okay
we take quite a bit of data and yeah you
know when we're running one of these
analyzes even if the CPU is full we're
not using more than a few thousand at a
time this is of course just for one
pipeline there's several pipe there's
many pipelines that are analyzing the
data all at once so there's definitely
several thousand CPUs in usage but it's
not obscenely heavy okay so if you're
Gathering data over a year then how long
can it take for you to get some actual
maybe go back to the beginning for us
real quick and then tell us how the
software actually functioned to get you
an answer I mean we you know when did
ligo start when was it operational you
get a Year's worth of a gigabyte per
second when do you start getting answers
yeah so I mean ligo probably first
started collecting data I never remember
if it was the very end of the 90s when
the data collection turned on or very
early to thousands but in its current
state the advanced Sligo detectors they
start started collecting data in 2015
and typically what we'll do is we'll
observe for some set period of time shut
down the detectors perform some upgrades
to make it more sensitive and then
continue the process all over again
when we're looking to get answers to if
there's gravitational waves in the data
I guess there's really a couple of time
scales that we're interested in the
first is this you know low latency or
near real time time scale and at the
moment the pipeline that I work on can
analyze all of the data in about six
seconds or so as it's coming in so we
can pretty rapidly identify when there
is a candidate gravitational wave
there's a number of other enrichment
processes that we do on each of these
candidates which means that by the from
the time of data collection to the time
of broadcast to the broader world
there's maybe 20 to 30 seconds of
additional latency but overall we still
are able to make those statements pretty
fast on a higher time scale side of
things when we want to go back and look
in the data and have a final say on you
know what's in there and we don't want
to have to worry about the constraints
of doing this in near real time that
process can take a little bit longer it
can take of the order of a couple of
months and this is really a feature of
a couple of things maybe how we're
cleaning the data and making sure that
we're waiting for all of those pipelines
to finish up how we're calibrating the
data waiting for those to finish up and
then also just tuning the actual
detection pipelines so that they're
giving us the best results that they
possibly can and how do you do that how
do you know that your error correction
is working and your calibration is
working and is software helping you to
answer those questions
yeah definitely I don't know as much
about the calibration pipeline it's it's
a complicated thing I don't want to
speak too much on that but it certainly
helps us with the actual search for
candidates and helping to identify them
it has to be tricky though right because
your error correction can introduce art
or your calibration can calibrate in a
way that introduces something that may
be a false signal I'm not sure how
familiar you are with that part of the
process but that seems like a pretty
significant challenge yeah so the
calibration I don't think it would ever
have that large of an effect when I say
calibration I really mean the mapping
between that interference pattern and
the distance that these mirrors inside
of our detector are actually I see I see
so it's more about ensuring that the
data we're collecting is corresponding
to the physical reality and these are
kind of aligned exactly and so our
initial calibration is already pretty
good and it's these subsequent processes
that help just reduce our uncertainties
by a couple extra percent but it would
not have the impact of introducing a
spurious candidate or anything like that
in the data so if I'm understanding this
correctly it seems like very early on in
the after the data collection and
calibration process you're able to do
some initial analysis of this data and
so while we're collecting a gigabyte of
data per second we don't necessarily
treat every gigabyte of data the same
because of that initial analysis is that
correct meaning some data is more
interesting than others yeah exactly so
you know packaged in with that gigabyte
of data is a number of different data
streams we're really just interested in
one of those streams you know to help
further mitigate the size of the files
that we're analyzing and creating we
down sample the data to two kilohertz as
well so we are able to reduce the
storage capacity for the output of the
analysis by quite a bit when we do these
archival analyzes I guess just to give a
little bit of context when we do the
archival analyzes over maybe five days
of data we're typically dealing with
candidate databases well let me be even
more careful they're not even candidate
databases but analysis directories that
are somewhere of the order of a terabyte
or two so there's there's clearly quite
a bit of data reduction that happens
between ingesting the raw data and
writing out our final results
okay and when you say down sampling
would that be equivalent to say taking a
MP3 file that's at a certain sampling
rate and then reducing the sampling rate
which means you'll lose some of the
Fidelity and the quality of the original
recording but you'll maintain enough
information so that you can enjoy the
song or in your case enjoy the the
interference pattern of gravitational
waves
yeah that's exactly right at the moment
if you were to take a look at where our
detectors are most sensitive to in the
frequency space you'll see that our real
sweet spot is somewhere around like 100
to 200 Hertz so if we're sampling at 16
kilohertz that is a lot of resolution
that we don't necessarily need when
we're interested in such a small band
now of course we're interested in more
than just the one to 200 Hertz region
but we still lose sensitivity pretty
rapidly As you move to higher
frequencies so that extra frequency
content is something that we don't need
to worry about at least at the detection
side for now interesting so the analogy
is quite pertinent because you know 16
kilohertz is CD quality sound if you
know you're old like me and you remember
CDs before we just had Spotify and
whatever we have now and of course even
if you're at 100 200 they're still
harmonics and there's other resonant
frequencies but you're literally able to
chop off some of those higher
frequencies reduce the sampling rate and
then you can deal with a much smaller
data set yeah exactly to give some
context here when we're looking for a
binary black hole in spiral we really
expect the highest frequencies that like
the standard emission reaches to be
hundreds of Hertz maybe not above like
six 800 Hertz something like that for
binary neutron stars we expect this to
be a bit higher but still nowhere near
the 16 kilohertz bound right or even the
two to four K I think that's about the
human voice range we're talking very
very low low frequencies yeah although
it's interesting that they're not as low
as I might have expected I mean isn't
that within the human auditory not that
we could hear a gravitational wave I'm
just saying the Hertz itself that's an
audible frequency which is interesting
there's actually a lot of fun animations
and audio clips online that show what
the power deposited in a detector from a
gravitational wave looks like and then
you can listen to that gravitational
wave as time progresses so you can hear
what frequencies the wave is depositing
power in the detector at so of course
you know it's not an actual sound that
like you could hear
sound and it's really nice yeah that's
really cool we'll have to find some
links in the show notes and if you can
share some that would be fun for I think
listeners to be able to go and actually
I'll put it in quotes you can't see me
doing this but here gravitational waves
yeah sort of like watching a sci-fi
movie and you can hear the explosions
and you say well okay we know we can't
really hear them but it's it's fun
so large volumes of data both collection
time as well as in later analysis and
processing time I imagine because of the
nature of what you're doing as well
there's also certain aspects of data
security and public record requirements
that you have to deal with as well so
maybe speak to our listeners some about
how that affects what you do and how
software either helps or hinders in
those aspects you had mentioned earlier
with broadcasting that like a true
broadcast anybody can kind of just
listen into the difference with the data
that we're analyzing is that it's
proprietary for some period set forth in
you know our NSF agreements so it's only
broadcast to very specific sites and
it's eventually publicly released later
on so we do need to have different ways
of authenticating the users when we're
trying to access data before this public
period has commenced and then once it's
commenced it's it's fine anybody can
access it from anywhere yeah so to
actually access this data and to make
sure that you know we're properly
authenticated we use a couple of
different methods the first method which
is maybe the easiest is just with SSH
keys so we have you know a protected
database somewhere we can upload our
public SSH key and that'll allow us to
access the different Central Computing
sites that we might want to use now once
we're on one of these sites if we want
to access any data that's still
proprietary we use x509 certification to
authenticate ourselves and make sure
that we can access this data okay so SSH
key sharing and then as well as public
private key encryption which is pretty
standard stuff I mean x509 is what SSL
uses under the covers anyway so it's
pretty standard protocols there so does
the use of software ever get in the way
or create additional challenges I think
maybe sometimes you know we've done
definitely been making this push to
formalize things in Academia a little
bit more so to maybe have some better
software practices so to make sure that
we actually carry out reviews we have
teams review things approve all of these
different merge and pull requests Etc
but what we can run into especially when
we're analyzing data in low latency is
that we've got these fixes that we want
to deploy to production immediately but
we still have to deal with getting
things reviewed and of course this isn't
to say that review is a bad thing at all
it's just that you know as we move
towards the world of best software
practices you know there's a lot of
things that come with it and we've
definitely had some Growing Pains at
times with making sure that we can
actually do things as quickly as we want
to when there's time sensitive data
coming in yeah it sounds like it's very
equivalent to the feature grind which is
what we call it business software world
so maybe tell us a little bit about that
what are those kinds of things that you
might say oh we need to update or we
need to get this out there and what are
the pressures on you that lead to those
kinds of requirements for change in the
software yeah so when we're going into
our different observing runs we always
make sure that we're in the best
possible state that we can be the
problem is that of course nature is very
uncertain the detectors are very
uncertain there is always something that
we didn't expect that will pop up and
the way that this manifests itself in
our analysis is in retractions so
retractions are basically when we
identify a gravitational wave candidate
and then realize quickly or otherwise
that it is not actually a gravitational
wave but just some type of noise in the
detector and this is something that we
really want to avoid number one because
we really just want to announce things
that we expect to be astrophysically
interesting and number two because
there's a lot of people people around
the world that take in these alerts and
spend their own valuable telescope time
trying to find something associated with
that particular candidate event and so
thinking back to previous observing runs
a lot of the times where we wanted to
hot fix something or to where because we
wanted to fix the pipeline to avoid
whatever new class of retractions was
showing up so you know we can get used
to the data in advance of the observing
run but if something unexpected comes up
we might find a better way to deal with
the noise we just want to get that
implemented as quickly as possible and
so I would say that most of the time
when we're dealing with you know rapid
review approval it's because we're
trying to fix something that's gone awry
and that makes sense like you said you
want to prevent people from essentially
going on a wild goose chase when they're
just going to be wasting their time and
their resources and if you discover a
way to prevent that you want to get that
shipped as quickly as you can so that
you can at least mitigate the problem
going forward yeah exactly do you ever
go back and sort of Replay or
re-sanitize the streams after the fact
if you discover one of these retractions
had a significant impact on a you know a
run yeah I guess we re-sanitized the
streams by these different
noise mitigation pipelines that can
clean up the data and this is normally
what we wind up using in our final
analyzes that are maybe months along
down the line in terms of doing
something in maybe medium latency of the
order of minutes to hours or so if we're
just trying to clean things up we
normally just change the way we're doing
our analysis in a very small way we just
tweak something to see if we were
correct about our hypothesis that a
specific thing was causing this
retraction
an analogy keeps coming into my head as
you're talking about processing this
data it's reminded me a lot of audio
mixing and how you have all these
various inputs but you might filter and
stretch or correct or these kind of in
the end what you're looking for is this
finished curated product that reflects
you know the best of your musicians in
the best of their abilities in a way
that's pleasing to the listener and this
sounds like there's some similarities
here between what you're trying to do
too there's actually a remarkable number
and I probably should have led with this
at some point that so the pipeline that
I work on the detection pipeline I work
on is called GST lau and the name GST
comes from gstreamer and Lao comes from
the ligo algorithm library now gstreamer
is an audio mixing software so we are
built on top of those capabilities
and here we are creating a podcast where
after this people will take our data and
they will sanitize it and they will
correct it and they will publish it for
our listeners listening pleasure and of
course we've also taken Lego waves and
turned them into equivalent sound waves
so it all comes full circle thank you by
the way Claude Shannon for your
information theory that we all benefit
so greatly from and we'll put a link to
the show notes about that
let's talk a little bit about simulation
and testing because you did briefly
mention unit testing before but I want
to dig a little bit more into that it's
specifically too if you can speak to are
you running simulations beforehand and
if so how does that play into your
testing strategy and your software
development life cycle
we do run a number of simulations to
make sure that the pipelines are
operating as expected and we do this
during the actual analyzes themselves so
typically what we do is we decide what
types of astrophysical sources we're
interested in so we say we want to find
binary black holes or binary neutron
stars and we calculate for a number of
these systems what the signal would look
like in the ligo detectors and then we
add it blindly to the detector data and
analyze that data at the same time that
we're carrying out the normal analysis
and so what this allows us to do is to
search for these known signals at the
same time that there are these unknown
signals in the data and it provides
complementary information because by
including these simulations we can
estimate how sensitive our pipeline is
we can estimate you know how many things
we might expect to see in the true data
and it just lets us know if anything's
going going awry if we've lost any type
of sensitivity to some part of the
parameter space or not something that's
a little bit newer as of maybe the last
year or so a number of really bright
graduate students have added this
capability to a lot of our monitoring
software in low latency and so now we're
doing the same thing there where we have
these fake signals inside of one of the
data streams and low latency and we're
able to in real time see that the
pipeline is functioning as we expect
that we're still recovering the signals
that sounds very similar to a practice
that's emerging in the software industry
which is testing and production so what
you just described because initially in
my mind I was thinking maybe before you
run the software you run some
simulations and you sort of do that
separately but from what you just
described you're doing this at real time
and now you you know you injected a
false signal of course so you're able to
you know distinguish that from a real
signal but the fact that you're doing
that you're doing that against the real
data stream in in real time yeah that's
true I would argue even in these
archival analyzes we don't normally do
any type of simulation in advance of the
analysis normally just concurrently
okay that's really interesting and then
of course the testing is that's part of
the simulation is you're using your test
to verify that the simulation results in
what you expect and everything's
calibrated correctly and and all sorts
of things yeah exactly yeah that's
really cool and again hopefully you know
as listeners are learning from this
there is that bit of bifurcation between
you know business software or streaming
you know media software versus the the
world of scientific software and yet I
think there's some really interesting
parallels that we've been able to
explore here as well so are there any
perspectives of physicists generally
like just broad perspective of
physicists that have been helpful for
you when you think about software
engineering and how to apply software to
what you do
I think one of the biggest things maybe
impressed upon me through grad school
was that it's very easy especially for
scientists to maybe lose track of the
bigger picture and I think that's
something that is really useful when
designing software because I know when
I'm writing codes sometimes it's really
easy to get bogged down in the minutia
try to optimize everything as much as
possible try to make everything as
modular and disconnected as possible but
at the end of the day I think it's
really important for us to remember
exactly what it is we're trying to find
and I find that by stepping back and
reminding myself of that it's a lot
easier to write code that stays readable
and more usable for others in the long
run yeah it sounds like don't lose the
forest for the trees yeah exactly
surprisingly easy to do because you know
you'll have this very broad physical
problem that you're interested in but
the more you dive into it the more easy
it is to focus on you know the minutia
instead of the bigger picture yeah I
think that's very equivalent in business
the software where you can lose sight of
what are we actually trying to deliver
to the customer and you can get so
bogged down and focused on this this
operation this method this line of code
and and that now and there's times where
you need to optimize it and I guess you
know that's going to be similar in in
your world as well so then how do you
distinguish that for example when do you
need to dig into the minutia and what
helps you identify those times when
maybe a bit of code does need a little
bit of extra attention versus
discovering yourself oh shoot I think
I'm bogged down and coming back up for
air like what kind of helps you you know
distinguish between those for me you
know my approach to code is normally
write something that works first and
then go back and optimize it later on
and if I run into anything catastrophic
along the way then that's a sign to go
back and rewrite a couple of things or
or reorganize stuff there so speaking of
catastrophic failures can you speak to
an incident where maybe you ship
something into the pipeline and
immediately everybody had a ah like oh
no moment and then you had to scramble
to try to get things back where they
needed to be you know I don't know if I
can think of an example offhand of where
we had shifted into production but I can
think of a couple of times in early
testing where I had implemented some
feature and I started looking at the
output and I realized that it made
absolutely no sense and in the
particular case I'm thinking of it's
because I had a normalization wrong so
the numbers that were coming out were
just not at all what I expected but
fortunately I don't have like a real
go-to answer of that in production that
would be a little more terrifying well
that's fine but what signaled to you
that was a problem like maybe explain
what you mean by a normalization problem
and then how did you discover it and
then how did you fix it before it did
end up going to production yeah so by
normalization I really mean that we are
making sure that the output of the
pipeline is
set to produce some specific value of
numbers under a noise hypothesis so that
if we have actual we like to assume
gaussian distributed noise in our
detectors so if we have gaussian noise
we expect the output of some stage of
the pipeline to give us numbers between
you know A and B so similar to Music Man
negative one to one like a sine wave
right you're getting it normalized
within this range so it doesn't go
outside of range and then you get
Distortion which of course in rock and
roll you want but in physics we don't
exactly and normally you know if we get
something outside of this range when
we're running in production it's
indicative that maybe the data just
doesn't look so good right there but you
know when I was testing this particular
patch I was only getting stuff outside
of this range which indicated to me I
had either somehow lucked upon the worst
data ever collected or I had had some
type of typo to my code Occam's razor
the simplest answer is probably the
right one well
what's interesting about that is when I
think about business software you know
you you do have one advantage which is
because you're dealing with with things
that are physically real we don't need
to get philosophical about what I mean
by real there but things that are
physical then you have a natural
mechanism that's giving you a corrective
whereas sometimes in business software
if you're building a feature there's not
necessarily a physical correspondent
that tells you if you're off track the
only thing you have is ask the customer
or watch the customer and see how they
interact with it you don't have
something to tell you but well you're
just out of you're out of range like
what does that even mean I am very
grateful of that because even the most
difficult problems that I I tackle I can
at least normally come up with some a
priority expectation of what range I
expect my results to be in and that can
help me narrow down potential problems
very very quickly and I'd imagine you
know if I was just relying on feedback
from others that that would be a much
longer and more iterative process yes
and our priori assumptions are
incredibly dangerous when you're trying
to discover the best feature or solution
for a customer
because we all know the rule of what
happens when you assume which I won't go
into right now but yes you have to be
very very cautious so yeah that that
sounds like a actually a significant
advantage of what you're doing although
it might be interesting to explore are
there ways to get signals in in business
software that are maybe not exactly akin
to but could provide some of those
advantages but that would be a whole
other whole other podcast episode
so maybe give us a little bit more
detail you mentioned some of the
languages before that you're using what
about platforms what cloud maybe
services are you using and what
development environments are you using
give ourselves our listeners a sense of
the flavor of those things if you can
yeah so at the moment we package our
software and Singularity every once in a
while we release Conde distributions as
well although we've been maybe a little
bit slower on updating that recently as
far as cloud services go there's
something known as the open science grid
which we've been working to leverage
this is
maybe not a true cloud service it is
still you know dedicated Computing for
scientific purposes but it's available
to you know groups around the world
instead of just one small subset of
researchers and because of that it still
functions similar to cloud computing and
that we have to make sure that our
software is portable enough to be used
anywhere and so that we don't have to
rely on shared file systems and having
everything you know exactly where we're
running the analysis we are working to
you know hopefully eventually use
something like AWS I think that'd be
really nice to be able to just rely on
something at that level of distribution
but we're not there quite yet okay and
then what about development tools and
development environments what are you
coding in you know day to day what is a
typical day of software coding look like
for you yeah so you know it's funny you
say that I think I always use them and I
know a lot of my co-workers use them
plenty of people also use Ides I don't
know if this is just a side effect of
the fact got a lot of the development I
do and my collaborators do is on these
Central Computing sites that you know we
have to SSH into but there's maybe not
as high of a prevalences of Ides as as
you might expect although maybe I'm just
behind the times at this point no
actually that's about what I expected
especially when you talk about the
history of the internet right it goes
back to defense and academic Computing
and that was what you did you SSH
through a terminal shell and then you go
in and you do your work using Vim
because well what else are you going to
do so that's that's not surprising to me
but you know again trying to give our
listeners a flavor of what's going on in
that space and yeah so that's
interesting that and not surprising that
those are the tools that you're using
what about operating systems are you
using proprietary operating systems
custom flavors or using standard
off-the-shelf forms of Linux or
something else pretty standard stuff
most of what we do is some flavor of
scientific Linux yeah and then is that
these like Community built kernels are
these things things that maybe you
you've custom prepared for what you're
doing that I'm not as sure on I think
there's some level of customization but
I I think a lot of it's pretty off the
shelf okay so there's some standard
scientific Linux maybe multiple flavors
but they're sort of a standard set of
hey this is what we kind of get when
we're doing scientific work and we can
sort of use that as a foundational
starting point yeah yeah that's pretty
cool what about open source software is
there any contributions that you make or
others on your team make or any open
source software that you use to do your
work or is it mostly internal other than
the scientific Linux which I imagine
there there might be some open source
aspects to that pretty much everything
that we use I think is open source so
all of the code that we write is open
source under the standard GPL license
you know we use pretty much any standard
python package you can think of but we
definitely strive to be as open source
as possible we don't often get
contributions from people outside of the
scientific Community but we have had a
handful okay well listeners challenge
accepted
all right
so I asked you previously if there were
perspectives you found helpful from a
you know a scientific and physicist
standpoint when you're thinking about
software engineering but is there
anything that maybe has gotten in the
way or ways of thinking you've had to
overcome to transfer your knowledge into
the world of software engineering yeah
definitely so I think one of the best
and arguably worst things about physics
is how tightly it's linked to math and
so you know as you go through graduate
school you're really used to being able
to write down these precise expressions
for just about everything and if you
have some type of imprecision you can
write an approximation to some degree
that is extremely well measurable and I
think one of the toughest things about
writing these software about software
engineering and about writing data
analysis pipelines is getting used to
the fact that in the world of computers
you sometimes have to make additional
approximations that might not have this
very clean and neat formula that you're
so used to writing you know thinking
back to graduate school I remember
thinking numerically sampling something
was just so unsatisfying because it was
so much nicer to just be able to write
this clean analytic expression that gave
me exactly what I wanted and I I just
recall that there's plenty of instances
like that where it takes a little bit of
time to get used to but I think by the
time you know you've got a couple of
years experience with the foot in both
worlds you kind of get past that yeah
and I think that's part of the
challenges we're trying to put
abstractions on abstractions and it's
very challenging and complex for our
minds and sometimes we think we know
more than we know and it's good to
challenge our own assumptions and and
get past them sometimes so very
interesting
well Ryan this has been a really
fascinating conversation and if people
want to find out more about what you're
up to where can they go so I have a
website Ryan mcgee.com which I try to
keep updated with recent papers research
interests and my CV okay great so that's
r-y-m-a-g-e-e.com Ryan mcgee.com for
listeners who are interested well Ryan
thank you so much for joining me today
on software engineering radio yeah thank
you again for having me Jeff this is
Jeff Doolittle for software engineering
radio thanks so much for listening
[Music]
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening
[Music]
foreign